Guide to the Jacob Gould Schurman papers, 1867-1942 [1986].
Schurman, Jacob Gould papers, 1867-1942 [1986].
- Series II. Schurman Articles, Speeches, And Books, 1875-1941 (Reel 48-51)
  - "Although the question of class organization is entirely in the hands of the students..." (Box 12, Folder 58)
  - "Wir leben in einer Zeit der so rasch auf einander..." (Box 12, Folder 59)
  - "Military Education in School and College" (Box 12, Folder 60)
  - "The Ethics of War", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 61)
  - "I never miss an opportunity to come to this beautiful and romantic city..." (Box 12, Folder 62)
  - Heute morgen habe ich einige Worte über die Anfange..., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 63)
  - "I said something this morning regarding...", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 64)
  - "This is a meeting of citizens irrespective of party...", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 65)
  - "Es ist mir eine Freude...", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 66)
  - "Every age has its own problems to solve...", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 67)
  - "It gives me particular pleasure to be able...", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 68)
  - Several fragments, single pages, partial manuscripts and typescripts without date. (Box 12, Folder 69-70)
  - Universität Heidelberg., 19271928 (Box 12, Folder 71)
  - "The Reaction of Graduate Work on the Other Work of the University", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 72)
  - Inaugural Address., 1892 (Box 12, Folder 73)
  - "The Future of Liberal Religion in America", 1892 (Box 12, Folder 74)
  - Books by Jacob Gould Schurman:
    - The Ethical Import of Darwinism, 1887 (Box 13)
    - Belief in God, 1890 (Box 13)
    - The Balkan Wars 1912-1913 1914 (two editions) 1916 (third edition) (Box 13)
    - Agnosticism and Religion, 1896 (Box 13)
    - Philippine Affairs - A Retrospect and Outlook, 1902 (Box 13)
  - Volumes including writing by Jacob Gould Schurman:
    - Inauguration of President Schurman, 11 Nov. 1892 (Box 13)
    - Peking Leader Reprints, "Extraterritoriality and its Gradual Relinquishment" 1925 (Box 13)
    - United States Political Reprints, Speech in honor of the Board of Filipino Commissioners, 1904 (Box 13)
    - United States Political Pamphlets "America's Duty to the Philippines," n.d.; "Philippine Fundamentals," n.d. (Box 13)
    - A Generation of Cornell 1868-1898, 1898 (Box 13)
    - The Lakeside Magazine "The Student's' Ward," n.d. (Box 13)
    - Bulletin of the American Geographical Society; "The Philippine Islands and Their People" 1900 (Box 13)
    - Report of the Philippine Commission to the President, 1900 volumes 1-4 (Box 13)
    - The Philippine Commission Report (Box 13)
  - Biographical Articles on Jacob Gould Schurman:
    - Jacob Gould Schurman in The Bookbuyer 1893 (Box 13)
    - Jacob Gould Schurman: Scholar, Political Activist, and Ambassador of Good Will, 1892-1942 by Maynard Moser, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Jacob Gould Schurman and the Formation of American Philippine Policy, 1899-1900 by Kenneth P. Davis (partial) (Box 13)
    - William Schurman, Loyalist by Dorothy Schurman McHugh (Box 13)
    - 1386-1961: 575 Jahre Ruprecht-Karl-Universität Heidelberg (Box 13)
- Series III. Subject Files, 1881-1940, [1986] (Reel 52)
  These files concern Germany, the Philippines, and China; also Cornell University, United States political affairs, international relations, and education. The series includes a few of Schurman's personal papers, financial information, and miscellaneous notes and drafts. Also, material relating to the February 8, 1986 "Schurman Day" at the University of Heidelberg, with articles about Schurman and his relationship with the University of Heidelberg by John Silber, Frank H. T. Rhodes, and Detlef Junker
  - Germany Subject File., n.d. (Box 14, Folder 1-34)
  - Philippines Subject File., n.d. (Box 14, Folder 35-40)
  - China Subject File., n.d. (Box 14, Folder 41-49)
  - Jacob Gould Schurman Personal Miscellany: holographic notes, financial information, personal notes., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1-9)
  - Cornell University Miscellany., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 10-18)
  - United States Political Miscellany., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 19-21)
  - International Affairs Miscellany., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Education Miscellany., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 23-24)
  - "The Cornell-Heidelberg Connection: Jacob Gould Schurman as Cornell President"by Frank H. T. Rhodes., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - "Jacob Gould Schurman, Heidelberg University and German-American Relations" by Detlef Junker., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - "Jacob Gould Schurman: Emissary of German Philosophy to America" by John R. Silber., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - "Democracy and Culture" by Richard R. Burt., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Remarks by General Glenn K. Otis on Schurman Memorial Day., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - "In Jacob Gould Schurman's Footsteps: Building Educational Bridges" by T. Benjamin Massey., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 30)
- Series IV. Clippings, 1892-1942 (Reel 55-56)
  A comprehensive project involved members of the staff of the President's Office and others in chronicling Schurman's career. In some cases, a newspaper printing of a speech delivered by Schurman is the only copy of the speech to be found in the collection. Caricatures of Schurman as printed in newspaper stories are in the clippings, as well as an account of his touting of Charles Evans Hughes for the Presidency of the United States, and his vigorous promotion of Philippine independence. Similarly, affairs in other parts of the world, and Schurman's interest in or involvement with these, can be traced in the clippings.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1892-1914 (Reel Microfilm 55)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1915-1942 (Reel Microfilm 56)
  - Philippines, 1896-1892 (Reel Microfilm 56)
  - China, 1904-1932 (Reel Microfilm 56)
  - Germany, 1925-1938 (Reel Microfilm 56)
  - Germany (Box 39)
- Series V. Photographs, 1867-1942 (Reel 54)
  Four main topics are documented photographically: the Philippines, Germany, China, and Schurman personal and family life. Formal and casual photographs are included, each style tracing Schurman's path from university president to international ambassador.
  - Philippines, 1899 (Box 18)
  - China, 1899-1933 (Box 19)
  - Sculptures (China), July 13-16, 1923 (Box 20)
  - Saxon National Library, 1929 (Box 21)
  - Germany, 1926-1928 (Box 22)
  - Germany, 1927-1928 (Box 23)
  - Germany, c. 1928 (University of Heidelberg). (Box 24)
  - Germany, 1961 (University of Heidelberg). (Box 49)
  - Family Photographs, 1867-1928 (Box 25)
  - Schurman Portraits, c. 1890 - c. 1939 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 27-28)
    Photographic Portraits of Jacob Gould Schurman; with President Taft, and Andrew Carnegie. Schurman in Japan, at home, and at Cornell University
  - Manchurian Railroad Photograph Album (Box 29)
- Series VI. Proclamations, Protocol And Social Material, Testimonials, And Ephemera, 1878-1939 (Reel 53, 55, 56)
  Many forms of material and documentation associated with Schurman and his personal and profession activities appear in this series, including many that document his fundraising for the University of Heidelberg and the reverent esteem for him that ensued. Examples of chinoiserie are included, and a temperance union scroll petition protesting Cornell student revelry and drunkenness on campus; notably, the first signatory of several hundred, is Liberty Hyde Bailey. Schurman family members' diplomas and Schurman's honorary degree diplomas are included. Other proclamations and diplomas acknowledge Schurman's many accomplishments and ventures, as well as his penchant for collecting art and other material representations of world culture.
  - Social cards, invitations, placecards, menus, and other protocol items
    - Cornell University (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - United States, 1896-1939 (Box 30, Folder 2-3)
    - Germany, 1925-1936 (Box 30, Folder 4-5)
    - China, 1921-1924 (Box 30, Folder 6-8)
  - Memorabilia
    - Liste Diplomatique, République de Chine, 1 Apr 1925, April 1, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - "Führer durch die Rüstkammer der Stadt Emden" 1927 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Address Book, Barbara Schurman, 1924 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Champagne and wine annotated booklet, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Medallion: "Für Ehrenvolle Verdienste Die Stadt Berlin" (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - "Stained glass from Verdun Cathedral, given me there Sept, 1918" (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia, ephemera, articles
    - Rosenthal Porzellan, 50 Jahre, decorative plate (Box 32)
    - Long, rolled, petition from the Clara M. Selkreg Woman's Christian Temperance Union, June 18, 1908, from Mary B. Wood, protesting student drunkenness at senior banquets. Contains many signatures. First signatory is Liberty Hyde Bailey. (Box 33)
    - Photocopy of WCTU petition in BOX 33. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - "Plan showing the Location of Car Parks for the Ball at Belvedere, Calcutta, 1934" (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - "Programm Zum Treffen Ehemaliger Heidelberger Studenten a Anlässlich der 575-Jahrfeir der Ruprecht-Karl-Universität Heidelberg im Mai 1961", May 1961 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Photocopy of Rhein-Neckar-Zeitung 2 Juni 1961, June 2, 1961 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Photocopy: "Oriental Art Collected by the Late Jacob Gould Schurman" (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Typescript: Calendar of Dalhousie College and University, Halifax 1883-1884, listing courses taught by Jacob Gould Schurman (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia, certificates, photographs
    - Photographs of Angkor Vat (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - Certificate: Universitati Ruperto-Carolae (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Book of signatures: "The Faculty of Cornell University to Jacob Gould Schurman, 1920" (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Book of signatures: "Resolutions of the Board of Trustees of Cornell University accepting the resignation of President Jacob Gould Schurman, February 28, 1920", February 28, 1920 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Book of Signatures to Mrs. Schurman from the Campus Club, signed by Anna Botsford Comstock (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Germany
    - University of Heidelberg items, certificates, and diplomas, 1928 (Box 36)
      Includes an address by Schurman and a response by Karl Heinsheimer, also a book "Das Schone" of paintings translated by Schurman.
    - Seating chart: "Tischordnung für Montag, den 25. November 1929", November 25, 1929 (Box 37)
    - Ticket: Olympischen 16 August 1936, August 16, 1936 (Box 37)
    - Seating chart: "Tischordnung bei dem Festmahle 4 März 1927", March 4, 1927 (Box 37)
    - "Address of Jacob Gould Schurman at the ceremonious act of presenting the Foundation in the Town Hall at Heidelberg on the 17th of December 1928", December 17, 1928 (Box 37)
    - "Aus der Matrikel der Universität Heidelberg Winter Semester 1878/79" (Box 37)
    - Book of signatures: "To His Excellency the American Ambassador Dr. Jacob Gould Schurman from Americans in Germany" (Box 37)
  - China
    - List: Members of the Welcome Association (Box 38)
    - Schedule: Royal Mail Steamship Line (Box 38)
    - Chinese writings, book of cartoon drawings with Chinese text. (Box 38)
- Series VII. Map Case items and Tape Recording
  - New York Times Illustrated Magazine Supplement, with Jacob Gould Schurman on the cover. Sheet music: "Alt Heidelberg, du Feine.", October 2, 1898 (Map-case N3)
  - Seating chart (encapsulated) for August 12, 1936 Olympic dinner. Also: Broadside: Philippine Proclamation. Broadside: Filipino Proclamation (Tagalog) (Map-case Y18)
  - Tissue rubbings: "These are prints made from stones on which have been carved pictures of these various vessels, the originals of which are in the exhibition at the Wu Men. This lot consists of sacrificial wine vessels used in ceremonial [sic] in the Chou Dynasty. PRJ August 2, 1924." "Rubbings from four Nestorian tablets near Sianfu PRJ." "The writer believes that these are rubbings from the tomb of an emperor of the T'ang Dynasty, T'ang T'aitsung. The names are the names of the horses. PRJ." (Map-case Y18)
  - Chinese text and drawings (Map-case Y18)
  - Chinese painted scroll presented to Jacob Gould Schurman celebrating his eightieth birthday, by Chevalier S. K. Chen, Shangai. (Map-case KK6)
  - Honorary doctorate from Dartmouth University, 1909-10-24 (Folder 1)
  - Certificate from the l'Ordre National de la Legion d'honnneur, 1918-12-27 (Folder 1)
  - Honorary doctorate from Harvard University, 1908-10-6 (Folder 1)
  - Honorary doctorate from Columbia University, 1892-06-08 (Folder 1)
  - Honorary doctorate from Dalhousie University, 1919-09-11 (Folder 1)
  - Honorary doctorate from University of Pennsylvania, 1917-02-22 (Folder 1)
  - University of Edinburgh First Class Certificate of Merit, 1877-1878 (Folder 2)
  - The Hill School completion certificate, 1913-06-10 (Folder 2)
  - Honorary doctorate from Brown University, Undated (Folder 2)
  - University College of London certificate of honour, 1877 (Folder 2)
  - MA degree from University of London, 1878-07-24 (Folder 2)
  - BA degree from University of London, 1877-11-14 (Folder 2)
  - Doctorate degree from University of Edinburgh, 1878-04 (Folder 2)
  - Honorary doctorate from Yale University (Folder 2)
  - Honorary doctorate from University of Missouri, 1919 (Folder 2)
  - Designation of representation in Chicago, signed by Governor Theodore Roosevelt, 1899 (Folder 3)
  - Commission document signed by William McKinley, 1899 (Folder 3)
  - University of Berlin document, 1879-10-29 (Folder 3)
  - Committee appointment letter from State of New York, 1915-10-07 (Folder 3)
  - Letter from the University of Aberdeen, 1907-01 (Folder 3)
  - Certificate from the German Red Cross, 1930-01-10 (Folder 3)
  - Sketch of Jacob Gould Schurman, 1930-01 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1876-1877 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1876-1877 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1875-1876 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1875-1876 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1875-1876 (Folder 3)
  - University College of London course certificate, 1875-1876 (Folder 3)
  - Image from Frankfurter Goethemuseum, Undated (Folder 3)
  - Scholarship certificate from University of Heidelberg, Undated (Folder 3)
  - Photograph of the Parthenon, Undated (Folder 3)
  - Oath of Allegiance and Office, Undated (Folder 3)
  - Letter from Princeton trustees, 1897 (Folder 3)
  - Document from University of Aberdeen, 1906 (Folder 3)
  - Membership certificate from the American Academy of Rome, 1905-04-25 (Folder 4)
  - Sketch of Jacob Gould Schurman from Peking, Undated (Folder 4)
  - Minister appointment to Greece and Montenegro signed by William Howard Taft, 1912-18-06 (Folder 5)
  - Minister appointment to China signed by Warren G. Harding, 1921-06-02 (Folder 5)
  - Ambassador appointment to Germany signed by Calvin Coolidge, 1925-03-17 (Folder 5)
  - American Philosophical Society certificate, 1908-04-25 (Folder 5)
  - Committee appointment letter from State of New York, 1905-10-19 (Folder 5)
  - Honorary Doctorate from Rutgers, 1920-07-17 (Folder 5)
  - Documents from Berlin, 1927-1930 (Folder 5)
  - Columbia University Nurses School certificate for Helen Schurman, 1920-12-01 (Folder 4)
  - Henry Street Settlement certificate for Helen Schurman, 1920-01-31 (Folder 4)
  - Cornell University BA degree for Robert Schurman, 1907-06-20 (Folder 4)
  - Presbyterian Hospital certificate for Helen Schurman, 1920-07-06 (Folder 4)
  - Rosemary Hall Connecticut degree for Barbara Schurman, 1917 (Folder 4)
  - Cornell University BA degree for Barbara Schurman, 1921-06-21 (Folder 4)
  - Badische Staastaministerium certificate, 1931-06 (Folder 6)
  - Tape recording tr5185a, Schurman Day, University of Heidelberg.
- Series VIII. Microfilm
  - All 56 reels are located in the mezzanine
- Series IX. Additional Memorabilia
  - Silver presentation box, 1925 (Box 40)
    Sterling silver box presented to "Jacob Gould Schurman as the Ameriacan Ambassador to Germany with the Affectionate Regard of his Peking Staff." Cover has engraved signatures of his staff.
  - Heidelberg University dedication album, 1960-1961 (Box 41)
    Album of items pertaining to the dedication of Schurman Hall at Heidelberg University in Germany and the painting and plaque there. In presentation box marked donated by Richard W. Kehrt in loving memory of his wife Suzanne D. Schurman, granddaughter of Jacob Gould Schurman.